Preliminary Inventory to the Jay Schaffner Papers TAM.526
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Jay Schaffner Papers
1950s-2010, bulk 1970-1990
TAM.526
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
25.0 linear feet (25 boxes)
Jay Schaffner (1952-), was an activist and official in the Young Workers Liberation League, a youth group affiliated with the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), of which he was also a member, and rom 1983-1991 Schaffner led the New York City-based Anniversary Tours, a travel agency associated with the CPUSA that organized trips to the Soviet Union and other socialist countries. Schaffner left the CPUSA in 1991 and joined the Committees of Correspondence, founded in 1991, and which in 2000 changed its name to the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism, which is a democratic socialist group largely formed by dissident members of the CPUSA, and was its treasure from 1993-2003. The papers contain records of the YWLL, CPUSA, COC/CCDS, and include convention discussion materials, reports, statements, notebooks, subject files, and clippings. There are also a single file on the Labor Youth League, a 1950s CPUSA affiliated youth organization; several each on Anniversary Tours and on the Greek Communist Party in the 1970s-1980s, some in Greek, and on Schafffner's 1976 trip to Greece to attend the congress of the Communist Youth of Greece. See also the box level description, below, under "Container List." NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Schaffner, Jay
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communist Party of the United States of America Records (TAM 132) contains a series of records of the Young Workers Liberation League.
Provenance
Gift of Jay Schaffner, 1/28/2010
Historical/Biographical Note
Jay Schaffner (1952-), was an activist and a leading official in the W.E.B. Du Bois Clubs of America, and its successor, the Young Workers Liberation League (YWLL), founded in 1979 (The YWLL changed its name to the Young Communist League in 1983), both youth groups affiliated with the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), of which he was also a member from 1968-1991, holding a variety of posts, including being a member of the National Organization Bureau and the Central Committee. Schaffner was also a CPUSA activist in Illinois in the late 1960s-early 1970s. In 1976 he attended the the congress of the Communist Youth of Greece, the youth group of the Greek communist party. From 1983-1991 Schaffner led the New York City-based Anniversary Tours, a travel agency associated with the CPUSA that organized trips to the Soviet Union and other socialist countries. and befor that, of Voices of the Future, a youth travel and speakers bureau. Schaffner left the Communist Party in 1991 and was a founding member of the Committees of Correspondence (COC), founded in 1991, which in 2000 changed its name to the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism (CCDS), which is a democratic socialist group largely formed by dissident members of the CPUSA, and has served as its New York Coordinator (1991-1993) and National Treasurer (1993-2003)and shas been a member of its executive board (1991-2005). He is also (1991 to date, i.e., 2010) a staff member of the American Federation of Musicians, Local 802, which represents musicians in New York City, Nassau and Suffolk counties, and is also one of the moderators of the progressive listserv, Portside.
Scope and Contents note
The papers contain records of the W.E.B. Du Bois Clubs of America, the Young Workers Liberation League, the Communist Party USA, the Committees of Correspondence / Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism, and include convention discussion materials, reports, statements, notebooks, subject files, and clippings. The materials cover the activity of Schaffner and these organizations in Illinois, New York, the United States, and internationally. There are also files on Schaffner's 1970 trip to North Vietnam, including his notebooks, clippings and other materials documenting student political activity at Niles Township High School (Illinois), a single file on the Labor Youth League, a 1950s Communist Party affiliated youth organization, several files each on Anniversary Tours, Voices of the Future, and on the Greek Communist Party in the 1970s-1980s, some in Greek, and on Schafffner's 1976 trip to Greece. See also box level description, below, under "Container List." NOTE: boxes are stored offsite and require advance notice for use.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. However, boxes are stored offsite and require advance notice for retrieval.
Anniversary Tours.; Committees of Correspondence (U.S.).; Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism (U.S.).; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Kommounistikon Komma tēs Hellados.; Schaffner, Jay; Schaffner, Jay; W.E.B. Du Bois Clubs of America.; Young Workers Liberation League.; Communism |z Illinois.; Communism |z New York (State); Communism |z United States; Communists |z Illinois.; High school students |x Political activity |z Illinois |z Niles (Township); Jewish communists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Niles (Ill.: Township); Socialism and youth |z United States.; Socialism |z New York (State).; Socialism |z United States.
- Young Workers Liberation League, 1969-1975 (Box 1)
- Young Workers Liberation League, 1976-1980 (Box 2)
- Young Workers Liberation League (1976-1984); Notebooks (1986-1977, beginning), 1968-1984 (Box 3)
- Notebooks (1968-1977, end) (Box 4)
- Notes and Speeches (1968-1980); Chicago (1968-1971, beginning) (Box 5)
- Chicago (1968-1971, end), undated (Box 6)
- Greek Communist Party; Jay Schaffner's Trip to Greece; CPUSA Educational Materials, 1970s-1980s (Box 7)
- Communist Party Documents, 1970s-1980s (Box 8)
- Communist Party Documents (1970s-1990s): Labor Youth League (1950s); Anniversary Tours, undated (Box 9)
- Communist Party pre-1991 Convention Discussion Materials; Various Subject Files; Communist Party (1969-1979, begin), 1969-1990s (Box 10)
- Communist Party (1969-1979, end); Communist Party USA and New York State (1979-1991, begin); Anniversary Tours, 1969-1991 (Box 11)
- Anniversary Tours; Communist Party, USA and New York State (1979-1991, end); Communist Party (1992-1994); Committees of Correspondence, aka COC (1991-1994), 1979-1994 (Box 12)
- Communist Party (1991-1994); Committees of Correspondence (1991-1994) (Box 13)
- Committees of Correspondence (National and New York State), 1992-1994 (Box 14)
- Committees of Correspondence, 1993-1998 (Box 15)
- Committees of Correspondence / Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism, aka CCDS (1993-2005); Subject Files; Tributes to Lou Diskin, Gil Green, Jack Spiegel, 1993-1999, undated (Box 16)
- Committees of Correspondence / Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism 1990-2005; Voices of the Future (Box 17)
- Committees of Correspondence / Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism, 1990s-2000s (Box 18)
- Committees of Correspondence / Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism, 1990s-2000s (Box 19)
- Schaffner's 1970 trip to North Vietnam (includes his notebooks); Niles Township High School, Skokie Illinois (clippings on student activism, etc.), 1970s; Voices of the Future, Anniversary Tours, 1980s., 1970s-1980s (Box 20)
- Jobs (includes music CD), Committees of Correspondence, and Alliance to End Repression and ACLU v. Chicago, 1970s-early 2000s (Box 21)
- Committees of Correspondence: Notes, Correspondence, Finances, and Conventions, 1990s-early 2000s (Box 22)
- Anniversary Tours, 1970s-1991 (Box 23)
- Anniversary Tours (1970s-1990) and Chronological Files (1963-1997) (Box 24)
- Chronological Files (1998-2010), Empire State College, and Scrapbook relating to Anniversary Tours, 1970s-2010 (Box 25)